TOM D'ROZA

SCRUM MASTER / TEAM LEAD AT BJSS

http://twitter.com/tdroza

Tom is a highly motivated individual with excellent technical and communication skills. An experienced professional software developer and technical team lead, with a career spanning twenty years in fields ranging from Enterprise Web, Mobile, Location Based Services, and currently working on a national healthcare system.

SKILLS

STUFF

EMPLOYMENT

Scrum Master, BJSS. Client: National Healthcare Provider 2013-05 — Present

Leeds, West Yorkshire, UK

Initially involved in analysis of the existing legacy application and bid preparation prior to winning the contract. Role involved 2-week on-site pre-elaboration phase focussing on examination of existing proprietary codebase for the legacy application, code metrics, functional analysis, detailed discussion with Business Analysts leading to requirements gathering, discussions with the client's own Technical Architects, and investigation into candidate technologies for the bid. Following the pre-elaboration, Tom was then heavily involved in the proposal document that formed the basis of the bid. Producing key sections of the document including comparison of web technologies and frameworks, database systems, CMS. Following a successful bid, Tom was heavily involved in the Sprint Zero and Elaboration activities, setting up Git repositores, build servers, project structure and the reference architecture. This role required close teamwork with the Technical Architects to refine and agree the project's code structure and key design patterns around separation of tiers, REST APIs, database transactions and audit, module structure and coding standards.

- Analysis of legacy application
- Successful bid for new work
- Elaboration
- Team lead

Agile Scrum Java Web Javascript AngularJS Git Quality

Software Engineer, BJSS. Client: International Commodities Trader

Leeds, West Yorkshire, UK 2012-12 — 2013-05

Tom joined this project as a software engineer during its final phase to assist with completing the functional development and bug fixing in preparation for a parallel run prior to go-live, where the new application was trialed alongside the existing legacy application. The role required Tom to familiarise himself with the existing codebase and a large number of integration points with other work-streams and APIs in order to contribute productively to project. Key challenges included working as part of a large team spread over multiple locations and a number of different suppliers, often poorly defined or with changing requirements and complex domain knowledge around commodities trading and invoicing.

- Scala
- Developer

Scala Java API

Software Engineer, BJSS. Client: International Commodities Trader

Leeds, West Yorkshire, United Kingdom 2012-12 — 2013-05

Responsible for the delivery of software components that receive events from other work streams to trigger the generation of cost items for Interest, Warehouse Rent, Transportation and Valuations. Costs are displayed to traders as a key tool to manage profit/loss. The application is a large scale distributed system using a broad mix of technologies including Scala, Ruby and C#. Tom's main development role focused on Scala and he adapted quickly to a new programming language, demonstrating an ability to 'hit the ground running' and make a valuable contribution to functionality, unit and component testing.

- Scala
- Java

Scala Ruby C#

Lead Software Engineer, BT.com

Martlesham, Ipswich, Suffolk, UK 2009-04 — 2011-07

Lead developer on BT.com eCommerce platform; Projects include the development of the Google powered search results page (using XML/XSLT and Zeus traffic manager) for BT Internet users, which receives over 1 million hits per day and generates significant advertising revenue; Strong emphasis on performance and stability. Key member of team working on complete redesign of the retail consumer MyAccount homepage and successfully delivered a new online order tracking application resulting in 30% improvement in successfully tracked orders, and 1000 fewer helpdesk calls per week. Leading a small on-shore development team as an exemplar of how a test driven, agile development methodology, coupled with experienced, skilled developers, can result in better quality deliveries.

- XML
- XSLT

XML XSLT Web Google

Lead Software Engineer, BT

Martlesham, Ipswich, Suffolk, UK 2008-01 — 2009-04

Lead developer for the BT.com Beta platform. Role involved design assurance, review and sign-off of designs and test plans, and technical leadership of development team. Striving to introduce an element of innovation into BT's online presence by launching new self-service applications in "beta" format. Applications that graduate from Beta status are migrated to the mainstream BT.com platform. Unsuccessful applications are quickly identified and reworked or "fail fast" thereby minimising wasted development expense. Tom led a small team of 3 developers to create a gadget framework based around the open source Apache Shindig project for use as a personalised portal for the top 15 BT Wholesale customers.

- JQuery
- lava

Javascript JQuery Java

J2EE Software Engineer, BT

Martlesham, Ipswich, Suffolk, UK 2005-12 — 2007-12

J2EE developer on BT.com Beta. Focusing on innovative new applications heavily influenced by emerging Web2.0 technologies and following Agile Delivery work practices. Responsibilities included rapid turnaround of prototypes, proof-of-concepts, high-level design, implementation, and close collaboration with Business Improvement managers to identify and capture the requirements that solve business problems. Other responsibilities include facilitator of Agile Scrum sessions, running daily stand-up meetings and weekly checkpoints. Particular focus on developing new applications around: Google Maps; Ajax, Widgets/Gadgets (iGoogle); 3rd party data APIs (ReST, XML, JSON) and Javascript frameworks (Jquery, prototype, scriptaculous etc).

- JQuery
- Google Maps
- Agile

Google Maps Javascript JQuery Agile

J2EE Software Engineer, BT

Martlesham, Ipswich, Suffolk, UK 2003-04 — 2005-12

Rewriting key consumer web applications for new WebLogic Portal platform. Release 1: worked on Access Control, focussing on Login & Registration. Responsible for implementation of key components of the website security. Release 2: Worked on Products & Services webapp, responsible for implementation of key back-end EJB components.

- Weblogic
- Access control

Weblogic Login Access control

Developer, BT

Martlesham, Ipswich, Suffolk, UK | 1999-07 — 2003-04

Joined BT, working on Webtrack, a web based fleet management and tracking application using GPS positioning and Inmarsat satellite/SMS messaging. Writing comms applications and developing for mobile devices (Windows CE). Responsible for creating a mobile application that was successfully trialled within BTPayphones. Developed mobile consumer applications based around SMS, personalisation and location, and resulting in an application prototype that was delivered into the BT Brightstar incuband Rocking Frog for commercial exploitation outside of BT. Performed customer contact role to Internal Ventures customer. Also supported external proposition development.

- SMS
- mobile

Location based services Satellite SMS mobile

EDUCATION

•

Sheffield College, Norton Centre

1994-09 — 1996-06

•

Abbeydale Grange School, Sheffield

1994-09 — 1990-06

8As, 2A*

•